Zeughofstr. 1 10997 Berlin Germany

Email: jonas.markgraf@gmail.com

Website: sites.google.com/jonasmarkgraf

### **Current Position**

2020 - ongoing: Senior Economist, Zalando SE, Berlin.

Expert for causal identification, statistics, and experimentation in the Algorithmic Data Products team at Zalando's Offprice Data Platforms & AI department.

Responsibilities include: measuring the impact of changes to the pricing algorithm; improving demand elasticity model; enabling to steer investment decisions to create deep customer relationships; leading a team of three on interim basis (6 months).

#### Education

#### Dr. rer. pol. Political Science, Hertie School of Governance, 2015 - 2018.

Thesis: Politicians as Bankers: On the Mechanisms and Consequences of Politically Influenced Banking.

Grade: summa cum laude.

Committee: Mark Hallerberg (Hertie School of Governance); Guillermo Rosas (Washington University in St. Louis); Joachim Wehner (London School of Economics).

o1/- o6/2017: Pre-Doctoral Research Fellow, Political Science Department, Washington University in St. Louis (sponsor: Guillermo Rosas).

11/2016: Short-Term Visiting Scholar, Juan March Institute, Carlos III University, Madrid.

M.Sc. International Political Economy, London School of Economics, 2013 - 2014.

B.A. Political Science & Economics, Free University Berlin, 2009 - 2013.

2011-2012: Erasmus Exchange, University of Kent, UK.

## **Previous Positions**

2019 - 2020: Policy Advisor, Federal Ministry of Finance, Berlin.

Economic advisor in the Directorate-General "Financial Market Policy" (Division: "International Anti-Money Laundering")

2018 - 2019: Postdoctoral Research Fellow, University of Oxford, Oxford.

ERC-funded research project WEALTHPOL on wealth inequality with Prof. Ben Ansell & Research fellow at Nuffield College

Responsibilities included: designing and implementing lab and survey experiments; quantitative data/text analysis; writing scientific papers and policy briefs; communicating results to diverse audiences; supervising PhD students.

#### 2015 - 2018: Research Associate, Hertie School of Governance, Berlin.

Research Project "Public Finance Through Public Banks" with Prof. Mark Hallerberg.

Responsibilities included: conceptualization of research project; presentation of findings; data collection.

#### 2014 - 2015: Consultant Market Analyst, International Trade Centre (UN / WTO), Geneva.

ITC-European Commission Business Survey on Non-Tariff Measures in the EU "Navigating Non-Tariff Measures"

Responsibilities included: coordination of survey launch; implementation of survey; organization and conducting of multi-day training workshops; survey design.

#### **Publications**

### Refereed Journal Articles

- 3. "Backscratching in Banks: Politically Motivated Appointments of Bank Managers.", Political Science Research and Methods, Early View
- 2. "On Board With Banks: Do Banking Connections Help Politicians Win Elections?" (with Guillermo Rosas), *The Journal of Politics*, 2019, (81) 4, 1357–1370.
- 1. "The Corporate Governance of Public Banks Before and After the Global Financial Crisis: Examples from Germany, Italy, and Spain." (with Mark Hallerberg), *Global Policy*, 2018, (9) S1, 43–53 (Special Issue)

#### Working Papers

"Borrowing Welfare: Credit Access and Support for Redistribution." (with Guillermo Rosas), invited to Revise & Resubmit at *The Journal of Politics* 

"Electoral Cycles in Bank Lending Explained: The Role of Political Representation in Governing Bodies." (with Till Stowasser)

"Voting Against Democracy: Feudalism and the Weimar Republic." (with Anselm Hager)

### Ongoing Projects

"How do wealth and income affect individuals' attitudes towards redistribution and taxation?" (with Ben Ansell & Asli Cansunar)

"How Credit Markets Shape Beliefs About a Just Redistributive System" (with Andreas Wiedemann)

#### **Policy Contributions**

The Distribution of Income and Wealth in Advanced Economies., WEALTHblog, University of Oxford, 2019.

Germany's savings banks: uniquely intertwined with local politics. (with Nicolas Veron), Bruegel, 2018.

# Conference Participation and Presentations

2020: APSA; PolMeth.

2019: EPSA; APSA; Dreilaendertagung.

2018: EPSA; MPSA; APSA; CES; SVPW; Dezernat Zukunft (invited talk); German Savings Bank Association (invited talk).

2017: EPSA; MPSA; SLAMM; Ronald Coase Workshop Bogota.

2016: Universidad Autonoma Barcelona (invited talk); Global Finance Workshop; CEU Graduate Network Conference.

# Fellowships & Grants

2019: John Fell Research Grant (Co-PI: Andreas Wiedemann) (£7,000).

2019: John Fell Research Grant & Nuffield College Politics Group (Co-PI: Andreas Wiedemann & Asli Cansunar) (£9,600).

2018: Weidenbaum Center Research Grant (PI: Guillermo Rosas) (\$3,000).

2018: Postdoctoral Swiss Government Excellence Scholarship, 2018-19 (CHF42,000) (declined).

2017: Ronald Coase Fellowship funding workshop participation (\$2,000).

2017: NASP Young Investigator Program funding participation at EITM & EPSA, ACRI (€ 3,000).

2014 - 2015: Carlo Schmid Scholarship for Fellowships in International Organizations, DAAD & Studienstiftung des Deutschen Volkes (~€ 10,000).

# **Additional Training**

2019: "Intermediate Causal Inference (Sensitivity & Placebo Testing)", Andy Eggers, University of Oxford.

2016 & 2019: "Quantitative Text Analysis", Heike Klüver, Humboldt University/Tom O'Grady, UCL.

2018: "Web Data Collection and Social Media Mining", Simon Munzert, Hertie School of Governance.

2017: "Empirical Implications of Theoretical Models (EITM) Europe Summer School", Turin.

2017: "Applied Statistical Programming", Jacob Montgomery, Washington University in St. Louis.

2017: "Longitudinal and Event History Models", Jeff Gill, Washington University in St. Louis.

2016: "Causal Inference in the Social Science", Elias Dinas, ECPR Summer School, Budapest.

### Skills

Software: R, Stata, IATEX, GitHub, SQL, Microsoft Excel (all advanced), Qualtrics, Python (intermediate), JavaScript (basic)

Languages: German (mother tongue), English (fluent), Russian (moderate), French (moderate)

# References

#### Ben Ansell

Professor of Comparative Democratic Institutions, University of Oxford.

## Mark Hallerberg

Professor of Public Management and Political Economy, Hertie School of Governance.

## Guillermo Rosas

Professor of Political Science, Washington University in St. Louis.